Guide to the Harris County Women’s Political Caucus Records
University of Houston Libraries
Harris County Women’s Political Caucus Records
1972-1983
02/2011-001
Texas Women's Political Caucus. Harris County Chapter
0.50 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection is comprised of one box and includes newsletters and correspondence from the Harris County Women’s Political Caucus and the Texas and National Women’s Political Caucuses, brochures, convention related documents and histories and bylaws of the organizations. It also includes a few issues of the Women’s Political Times, a publication of the National Women’s Political Caucus. Materials are arranged regionally, and then by topic within each regional series.
Historical Note:
The Harris County Women’s Political Caucus was founded in April of 1972 as one of the local affiliates of the Texas Women’s Political Caucus and National Women’s Political Caucus. The by-laws of the caucus defined its purpose as organizing Harris County women so that “they may unite in political action, especially against sexism, racism, institutional violence, and poverty.” (Bylaws, Folder 1, Box 1). Founding members of the Harris County Women’s Political Caucus included many well-known Harris County activists, business leaders, philanthropists and politicians such as Betty Barnes, Helen Cassidy, Peggy Hall, Ruth Milburn, and Poppy Northcut. Throughout the rest of the 1970s the Harris County Political Caucus was very successful in women’s rights advocacy. It collected data about discrimination against women, lobbied political leaders at the local and state level for pro-women legislation such as the ratification of the state and national Equal Rights Amendments, and supported the political campaigns of women seeking public office. The caucus also successfully lobbied for the creation of a Women’s Advocate for the city of Houston.
By 1981 the Harris County Political Caucus was one of the fastest growing affiliates of the National Women’s Political Caucus in the nation, having increased its membership by 260% (“A brief history” Harris County Women’s Political Caucus). The caucus continued its social and political activism in the 1980s, taking an active role in opposing anti-choice legislation in Texas and supporting the mayoral race of Kathy Whitmire.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Texas Women's Political Caucus; Texas Women's Political Caucus. Harris County Chapter
Genre/Form of Material:
Administrative records; Brochures; Bylaws (administrative records); Correspondence; Newsletters; Newspapers
Topical Term:
Equal rights amendments -- United States; Texas Equal Rights Amendment; Women -- Political activity
Accruals:
This collection is a compilation of items taken from the Houston Area Women’s Center Collection (1996-005), the Josephine Harris Stewart Papers (2000-001), the Houston Area NOW and Other Feminist Activities Collection (2002-003) and a donation by Barbara Karkabi.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Related Materials:
Houston Area Women’s Center Records(http://archon.lib.uh.edu/index.php?p=collections/controlcard&id=351)
Josephine Harris Stewart Papers (http://archon.lib.uh.edu/index.php?p=collections/controlcard&id=190)
Houston Area NOW and Other Feminist Activities Collection (http://archon.lib.uh.edu/index.php?p=collections/controlcard&id=459)
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection is comprised of one box and includes newsletters and correspondence from the Harris County Women’s Political Caucus and the Texas and National Women’s Political Caucuses, brochures, convention related documents and histories and bylaws of the organizations. It also includes a few issues of the Women’s Political Times, a publication of the National Women’s Political Caucus. Materials are arranged regionally, and then by topic within each regional series.
Detailed List of Contents
- Harris County Women’s Political Caucus, id118402
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the documents directly related to the Harris County Women’s Political Caucus, a local affiliate of the Texas and National Women’s Political Caucuses. Some of the items featured in this series are the bylaws and history of the organization, the operational and organizational documents of the organization, and a series of newsletters published by the caucus. The series includes 12 folders contained in 1 box.
  - Bylaws, history and other organization documents, id118406 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Officers and members, id118407 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, id118408 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Finance and fundraising documents, id118409 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Conventions, id118410 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Committees and Task Forces, id118411 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Endorsements, id118412 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Women in politics, reports for Texas and the nation, id118413 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters, 1973-1974; id118414 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newsletters, 1975-1977; id118415 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Brochures and pamphlets, id118416 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Affiliates, id118417 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Texas Women’s Political Caucus, id118403
  This series contains the documents directly related to the Texas Women’s Political Caucus and is comprised of 3 folders contained in 1 box.
  - By-laws and organizing conference, 1972; id118429 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Texas Women’s Political Caucus newsletter, 1973-1976; id118430 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Texas Women’s Political Caucus Conventions, id118431 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- National Women’s Political Caucus, id118404
  This series contains the documents directly related to the National Women’s Political Caucus. There’s an extensive set of documents related to the 1979 national convention, saved by Josephine Harris Stewart and removed from her collection for inclusion in this series. This series is comprised of 7 folders contained in 1 box.
  - Bylaws, 1978; id118433 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cincinnati National Convention, 1979; id118434 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cincinnati National Convention, 1979; id118435 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - National elections materials, 1979; id118436 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - National Women’s Political Caucus social and political issues, id118437 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - National Women’s political caucus t-shirt, id118438 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous, id118439 (Box 1, Folder 22)